I’m often asked
what my opinion
about a diet
or disease is.
Who cares what my or
anyone else’s opinion is.
All we should care about
is what the science says.
What does the best available
balance of evidence
Published in the peer-
reviewed medical literature
have to say right now?
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast,
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
Did you know that research
has consistently shown
that healthcare professionals
are biased
against people classified
as overweight or obese?
In our first story,
we look at how common
this problem is.
Described as the last “acceptable”
form of bias, weight stigma is
the rampant discrimination and
stereotyping of overweight individuals.
Fifty overweight women were asked
to keep a diary of all the times
they felt they were being
stigmatized for their weight.
Over a single week, more than
a thousand instances were recorded.
An overweight woman
may expect to be harassed
such as called names or insulted,
run into physical barriers
(like unable to fit into public seats),
or discriminated against
(such as perceived poorer service
at restaurants or stores)
on average about three times a day.
Obese men report three times
less discrimination than women
of the same size; so, maybe it’s
only a daily occurrence for them.
They’re not just being paranoid.
Studies using professional
actors presenting as job applicants
made up to appear overweight
with the Hollywood magic
of theatrical prostheses were
significantly more likely to be
discriminated against than when
appearing as their normal weight selves.
This employment bias was
found to be especially prejudiced
against overweight
women compared to men.
Attitudes can also be
explored in surveys.
In a comparison of 16
stigmatized social groups,
such as homosexuals and homeless
people, only drug addicts and smokers
were regarded with higher levels
of disgust than obese individuals.
The researchers did note, however,
there was effectively a tie:
obese people were “rated just
as disgusting as politicians.”
This weight stigma
starts surprisingly young.
Children as young as three years
old describe overweight peers as
“mean,” “stupid,” “lazy,” and “ugly.”
Then, there was that famous
study published back in 1961.
Children in summer camps
and schools across a swath
of different social, cultural,
and ethnic backgrounds
in California, Montana, and
New York were asked to rank
the following images as
to who they liked best,
including a child with crutches
with a brace on their leg,
a child in a wheelchair, a child
with one of their hands missing,
a facially disfigured child, or an obese child.
In every population of kids they tested,
there was “remarkable uniformity.”
The obese child always came in dead last
That was ages ago, though.
But in 2003, researchers published
the 40-year follow-up.
The study was repeated and...the
title of the study gives it away:
"The Stigmatization of
Obese Children"...getting worse.
The obese child was liked even less!
This parallels trends
throughout society with nearly
a 70 percent jump in
perceived weight discrimination
recorded in national surveys
since the mid-nineties.
Attitudes among teachers
may not be helping.
More than a quarter of teachers
and other school staff surveyed
felt that becoming obese
is “one of the worst things
that could happen to a person.”
Even parents can be biased,
providing less support for college
for their overweight daughters
compared to thinner siblings.
As two prominent obesity
researchers commented,
“It is a strong prejudice indeed
when parents discriminate
against their own children.”
What about doctors?
One representative national
survey found that more than
half of physicians
viewed obese patients as
“awkward, unattractive, ugly,
and noncompliant.”
About a quarter of nurses agreed
or strongly agreed to the statement:
“Caring for an obese patient
usually repulses me.”
This antagonism can have
serious health consequences
for those who may need it the most.
For example, obese women
are at higher risk
for developing cervical,
endometrial, and ovarian cancers;
yet, they are less likely to be screened.
Morbidly obese patients only
have about half the odds
of getting their
recommended pelvic exams.
Part of this may be avoidance
on the part of the patient,
but some doctors just turn
obese patients away.
The Sun Sentinel polled
OB/GYN practices in Florida
and found that as many as one
in seven refused to see heavier women,
for example, setting weight
cut-offs for new patients
starting at 200 pounds.
Even doctors who welcome
obese patients have been found
to give them short shrift.
Physicians randomized to
receive a medical chart
of a migraine patient
who was either presented
as average weight, overweight, or
obese said that they would give
the obese patient about
28 percent less of their time.
And it’s less quality time.
Recorded doctor’s visits
found physicians tend to build
less emotional rapport
with overweight patients.
Even obesity specialists
profess increasingly
explicit anti-fat attitudes.
Worsening in surveys taken
between 2001 and 2013,
obesity specialists described
fat people as significantly
more “lazy, stupid, and worthless.”
Even in the medical literature,
you’ll find lines like this,
an example from the Annals
of Internal Medicine:
“obesity is an aesthetic crime: it is ugly.”
The good news is they appear
to be able to hide their disdain.
In a study entitled “Obese patients
overestimate physicians’ attitudes
of respect,” despite the
negative attitudes doctors harbored
towards their obese patients,
the same patients expressed
their satisfaction with their providers.
The researchers concluded,
“While physicians may be
successfully playing the part,
the lack of true respect suggests...
the authenticity of the
patient–physician relationship
should be questioned.”
In our final story today we ask,
how might weight stigma
be a vicious cycle?
Although total fasting can
dramatically increase blood levels
of the stress hormone
cortisol, as much as
doubling within five days,
just dieting alone does not.
There is, however, a way
stress and obesity could
turn into a vicious
cycle: weight stigma.
Across thousands of individuals
followed for four years,
those reporting
discriminatory experiences
had more than twice the
odds of becoming obese.
And those who started out obese
had more than three times the odds
of staying that way compared
to those who started out
at the same weight but didn’t
experience discrimination.
Now, this could be from
stress-induced eating
on one side of the
calorie balance equation
or stigma-induced exercise
avoidance on the other.
Obese individuals with more
frequent experiences with
weight stigma report greater
avoidance of exercising in public,
feeling judged and embarrassed.
These “too fat to exercise”
fears may be well-grounded.
Strong anti-fat biases have
been documented in both
fitness professionals and regular
gym-goers, which may translate
into an unwelcoming environment in
fitness centers and health clubs.
Whichever side of the calorie
equation gets tipped,
those who experience weight
stigma can also end up suffering
health consequences
independent of any added weight.
Those reporting more frequent fat
prejudice exhibit higher levels
of depression, higher levels of
inflammation, and higher levels
of oxidative stress, as well
as a shorter lifespan.
Two studies following a
total of nearly 20,000 people
both found about a 50 percent
increase in mortality risk
among those reporting
greater daily discrimination.
Weight discrimination
may shorten life expectancy.
Despite these hazards,
some scholars advocate
for even more fat-shaming.
The President Emeritus of the
prestigious Hastings Center
infamously advocated for
“a kind of stigmatization lite,”
using social pressures to
compel people to lose weight
without resorting to
outright discrimination.
After all, he argued, what else
has the potential to counter
the persuasive force of the
billions spent in advertising
every year by the
food and beverage industry.
It worked against tobacco.
He recalls his own
battle with addiction:
“The force of being shamed and
beat upon socially was as
persuasive for me to stop smoking
as the threats to my health.”
The public health campaign to
stigmatize cigarettes turned
“what had been considered
simply a bad habit
into reprehensible behavior.”
When such campaigns have been
tried, they have been met
with fierce resistance though.
Georgia’s Strong4Life
campaign featured billboards of
morose-looking obese
children with captions like
“Warning: Chubby kids may
not outlive their parents” or
“It’s hard to be a little
girl when you’re not.”
The campaign sponsors defended
the ads as an attempt
to break through the denial
in a state with some of the
highest recorded
childhood obesity rates.
It’s only defensible, though, if it works.
Yale researchers found
that when normal-weight women
provided with bowls of M&M’s,
jelly beans, and chips
to snack on after watching
clips of stigmatizing material
like clumsy, loud, lazy
stereotypes getting teased
about their weight, they
eat about the same amount
compared to watching neutral
material such as insurance commercials.
But when overweight women
watch the same two sets of videos,
they triple their calorie intakes
after watching the stigmatizing scenes.
The researchers concluded,
“This directly challenges the notion
that pressure to lose weight in
the form of weight stigma will have
a positive, motivating effect
on overweight individuals.”
In other words, it could
make things worse.
Being labeled “too fat” in
childhood was associated with a
higher risk of becoming
obese compared to children
weighing the same who
were never told that.
But does that mean we should just
ignore the elephant in the room?
Many doctors apparently think so.
Just as veterinarians have
been found to be reluctant
to tell people their pets are obese,
fewer than a quarter of parents
of overweight children report
having been told by pediatricians
about their child’s weight status.
One might think it would be obvious,
but a Gallup Survey found
that parents appear to be
“notoriously poor judges
of their children’s weight.”
Similarly, the percentage of
adults who describe themselves
as overweight has remained
essentially unchanged
over the past few decades,
despite skyrocketing obesity.
All this, Gallup concluded,
helps “paint a picture of
mass delusion in the United
States about its rising weight.”
I think patients have
the right to be informed.
Those told by their doctor
that they are overweight
have about four times the
odds of attempting weight loss
and about twice the
odds of succeeding.
Just as smoking physicians
are less likely to challenge
their smoking patients, overweight
physicians are less likely
to bring up the subject of weight loss
or even document obesity in their charts.
Ironically, overweight
patients trust diet advice
from overweight doctors more
than docs who are normal weight.
Unfortunately, primary
care physicians appear
to have little to offer
in terms of specifics.
Fewer than half who were
surveyed said they provide
specific advice to their patients.
Just telling patients
to “watch what they eat”
is unlikely to be particularly helpful,
but many primary care physicians
may not even get that far.
Most physicians said they
would spend more time working
with patients on weight
management if only their time
was “reimbursed appropriately.”
Maybe we could offer a bonus to
refrain from blaming the victim.
One pair of commentators wrote
in response to the pro-stigma camp,
“If shaming reduced obesity,
there would be no fat people.”
I want to end this weight
stigma video series with the
jaw-dropping findings of a study
that I think best illustrates
how hard it is to
live inside a fat body.
If this doesn’t foster sympathy
among my medical colleagues,
I don’t know what will.
Researchers talked to men and
women who had lost and kept off
more than 100 pounds to
tap into their unique insight,
having personally experienced
what it was like to be
morbidly obese and then,
on average, 126 pounds lighter.
Forty-seven such
individuals were interviewed.
They were asked to think back
to when they were heavier
and make a choice: “If someone
offered you a couple of
million dollars if you
stayed morbidly obese forever,
would you have chosen the money?
Or would you have chosen to be
normal weight no matter what?”
Option #1 was, “I would have chosen
no money and being normal weight.
It would have taken me
about a second to decide.”
Option #2 was, “I probably would
have chosen being normal weight.
But the possibility of
having that much money
would make me think about the choice.”
Option #3 was,
“I wanted to be normal weight,
but I really could use the money.
If I would be a multimillionaire,
I think I could live
with being morbidly obese.”
One of the 47 had to think about it,
but the other 46 jumped at Option 1.
No one chose Option 3.
They all said they would give
up being a multimillionaire
to be normal weight.
If that shocked you,
buckle your seatbelts.
They were then asked about being
obese compared to other disabilities.
Normally, when you ask people
to choose between living with
their own disability or
switching to a different one,
there is a strong proclivity
to stay with their own.
For example, even though most people
would rather be deaf than blind,
blind people prefer to remain
blind by a large margin,
rather than having
sight without sound.
They already know how to cope
with their own disability,
and so there’s safety in familiarity.
However, the exact opposite happened
when the formerly obese were asked.
Every single one of the 47
said they’d rather be deaf
for the rest of their lives than obese.
Every single one said they’d
rather have difficulty reading,
be diabetic, have very bad acne,
or heart disease than be obese.
More than 90 percent said
they’d rather have a leg amputated,
and similarly, about 9 out of 10 said
they’d rather be blind
their whole lives than obese.
Obesity appears to be the
only handicap where nearly everyone
wants to switch, no
matter what the cost.
To quote one study subject,
”When you’re blind,
people want to help you.
No one wants to help when you’re fat.”
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
To see any graphs, charts, graphics,
images, or studies mentioned here,
please go to the Nutrition Facts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite to each of these topics.
For a timely text on the
pathogens that cause pandemics,
order the e-book,
audiobook, or hard copy
of my last book,
“How to Survive a Pandemic”.
For recipes, check out
my second-to-last book,
my “How Not to Diet Cookbook”.
It’s beautifully designed
with more than 100 recipes
for delicious and
nutritious meals.
And all the proceeds
I receive from the sales
of all my books goes to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
via bite-sized videos and articles.
Everything on the
website is free.
There’s no ads, no
corporate sponsorship.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.